Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, 1814-2005 (ongoing)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Miscellaneous manuscripts collection
1814-2005 (ongoing)
MS 226
9 boxes; 3 volumes (3.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection documents various aspects of the daily lives and activities of both famous and unknown women from diverse backgrounds. Materials include biographical sketches, correspondence, diaries, genealogies, photographs, memoirs, memorabilia, scrapbooks, and travel journals. A few well-known figures represented in the correspondence include Susan B. Anthony, Alice Stone Blackwell, Edward Hale, Julia Ward Howe, Frances Willard, Booker T. Washington, and Madame Chiang Kai-shek. Also included is a photo of Harriet Beecher Stowe; and autographed quotations by William Lloyd Garrison, Isabella Beecher Hooker, and Elizabeth Cady Stanton.
The Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection consists of biographical sketches, correspondence, diaries, genealogies, photographs, photograph albums, memoirs, memorabilia, postcards, scrapbooks, and travel journals dating from 1814 to 1987. This material documents various aspects of the daily lives and activities of women from diverse backgrounds. This collection is made up of individual items or groups of items that are too small to stand on their own as separate collections, but are otherwise unrelated.
About half of the collection dates from the nineteenth century and consists primarily of correspondence, diaries, and unpublished memoirs from unknown, or little known, women. Also included are a few letters from well-known figures such as Susan B. Anthony, Alice Stone Blackwell, Alice Morse Earle, Edward Everett Hale, Julia Ward Howe, and Frances Willard; a photo of Harriet Beecher Stowe; and autographed quotations by William Lloyd Garrison, Isabella Beecher Hooker, and Elizabeth Cady Stanton.
The twentieth century material is more varied. In addition to correspondence, diaries and memoirs, it includes many photographs (both loose and in albums), some genealogical material, and other miscellaneous memorabilia. Well-known figures represented in the correspondence include Booker T. Washington and Madame Chiang Kai-shek. The letters of Ellen Downes, a Naval secretary, written from Japan, Washington D.C., and Moscow between 1937 and 1948, are accompanied by photos and are very descriptive. A family photo album belonging to a woman identified only as "Gertrude" contains many interesting photographs, including some of Native Americans and some of cross-dressed women, taken in California, Albuquerque, and Canada, circa 1905 to 1913.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions are expected.
History of the Collection
Multiple donors have contributed to this collection.
Search Terms
Earle, Alice Morse, 1851-1911; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906--Correspondence; Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950--Correspondence; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909--Correspondence; Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910--Correspondence; Willard, Frances Elizabeth, 1839-1898--Correspondence; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915--Correspondence; Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897- --Correspondence; Family--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Recipes--History--Sources; Women--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Religion--History--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; New England--Social Life and Customs--19th century--Sources; United States--Description and travel--Sources
- Lillie Mae Bernice Alston, 1931-: memoir of her childhood in Mississippi, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Lucinda Andrus: commonplace book, 1837-40 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Mason Daniel Barrett, [See Box 8] (Box 1)
- Cornelia Middagh Birdsall, 1835-: memoir of life in Brooklyn and Quebec Province, [?]-1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Alice H. Burbank, [See Box 9] (Box 1)
- Joan Brumley Cooper: scrapbook, [See Box 3] (Box 1)
- Clara E. Cotter: commonplace book, 1850-56 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ellen Downes: letters, [See Box 3] (Box 1)
- Alice Morse Earle: correspondence, 1900-10, undated, [See also Books on Shelf] (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annie C.S. Fenner: Scrapbook, [See Box 4] (Box 1)
- Carolyn Galbraith
  - Correspondence
    - to friends from Grenfell Mission, Labrador, 1926-27, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - from teachers and students at Grenfell Mission, Labrador, 1926-35 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and memorabilia, 1920-27, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Martha Diman Gardner: Diaries, 1816-1892 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Ophelia Hoefling Gleason: memoir, photographs (mostly photocopies), and memorabilia, 1896- (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Louise (Dodge) Goodwin, Household Account Book, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Deborah Graff, [see box 11]
- Amanda Harwood Ferry Hall, 1828-1916?: memoir, begun 1906, and related material (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Julia Ward Howe: letters to Eliza Middleton, 5 Mar 1838; and 1 Feb and 4 Mar 1839 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Lucy Hunting [?]: Diary of a Girl, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- H. Louise Johnson: book of quotes and diary, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Janet Krogh: Scrapbook, [See Box 6] (Box 2)
- Fanny H. Lackey: commonplace book, circa 1863-85 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Levi Lamb: commonplace book, circa 1835-42 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Harriet McNeil: correspondence, 1814-19, (includes one 1849 letter from Ely to Harriet Burchard) (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Hedwig Meerman: letters to Margaret St. Julien Childs, and NACHRICHTEN (newsletter), 1981-87 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Maria Terese "Teri" O'Brien (1955-), [see box 10]
- Sarah Parkhurst: letters to her husband, William H. Parkhurst, Apr-Oct 1846 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Marian Prior: "In the Office" (typescript), and photographs (Box 2, Folder 7a)
- Katie Putnam: diary, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Clara M. Reed: European travel journals (2 vols.), Jun-Oct 1890 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Mrs. L.C. Robinson: letters and notes on religious religion, 1850-62 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Adaline Shaw: letter to Daniel Shaw, 28 May 1848 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Genevieve Bowen Shaw: correspondence (annual Christmas letters), biographical information, memorabilia, and photographs, circa 1916-62 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Lucille Tillinghad, personal account book, 1930-35 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Mary Ulery, diary exerpt, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Westerberg, Lila Ansell, Peace Corp Correspondence (Ghana), 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Joan Brumley Cooper: scrapbook of cross-U.S. trip, 1928 (Box 3)
- Ellen Downes: letters to Leila Wilson and Downes' mother from Japan, Washington, DC, and Moscow, 1938-48 (Box 3)
- Annie C.S. Fenner: scrapbook of original correspondence and published version of Rules for Good Living (WCTU, 1895) (Box 4)
- Anonymous family photographic album (Box 5)
- Janet Krogh (Smith 1934): World War II Scrapbook, 1943-1945 (Box 6)
- Flynn, Hulda Rees: Psychologist and Social Activist, Smith 1931 (Box 7)
  - Biographical information, articles, and correspondence, 1938-2005 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - FBI file, circa 1943-71 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
- Mason Daniel Barrett: correspondence 1927-45 (Box 8)
- Alice H. Burbank: correspondence to Esma W. Brown re: travel in Italy 1938-39 (Box 9)
- Deevey, Sharon: self-published books: Pretty Bland: Colorful Cooking for the Gastrointestinally Challenged, 2nd edition (2007); Lesbian Jottings, 1970-2010 (2010); Whines, Opines, and Lesbian Lines: Scattered Writings (2013) (Box 9)
- Maria Terese "Teri" O'Brien (Box 10)
  - "While I Danced Alone with the Moon Across the Front Yard," manuscript memoir of growing up in Haydenville, MA (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Family photographs and research materials (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Audio interview on CD with Evelyn C. Nickerson ("Aunt Lolly") (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Graff, Deborah: Peace Corps service in Costa Rica
  - General (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (typescript) to family and friends 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Earle, Alice Morse, Customs and Fashions in Old New England 1893
  - Home Life in Colonial Days 1900
  - The Sabbath in Puritan New England 1891